Finding Aid for Michigan Ecumenical Forum records, 1916-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Ecumenical Forum records 1916-2002
Michigan Ecumenical Forum.
27 linear feet
88326 Ba 2
Church organization, successor to the Michigan Council of Churches; established to facilitate interfaith cooperation and to promote ecumenical action on issues of social concern. Administrative and topical files relating to special projects and general activities, notably in the areas of Christian education, missions, and seminal issues such as world peace, environmentalism, and social justice.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the Forum (donor no. 7524 ) in February 1988.
The record group is open to research.
The History of the Michigan Ecumenical Forum (MEF) was one of evolution and growth. The organization's roots may be traced to 1860 when Sunday School advocates in Monroe, Kent, and Kalamazoo counties (and elsewhere across the state) coalesced to form the Michigan Sabbath School Association. Devoted to interchurch cooperation and as well as innovation and formalization in the Christian education of children and youths, the organization rapidly grew and by 1910 it reported having 518,000 Sunday school attendees statewide. It was formally incorporated as the Michigan Sunday School Association in 1916, appointed a general secretary I 1921, and in the following year changed its name the to the Michigan Sunday School Council of Religious Education (shortened in 1926 to the Michigan Council of Religious Education).
The Michigan Council of Churches (MCC) itself was not organized until 1928 and held its first annual conference in 1930. The impetus for this new organization came from the Detroit Council of Churches, which in collaboration with the New York-based Home Missions Council, gathered various denominational officials from the state with the stated purpose: "(1) to realize essential unity among the Christian forces of the State on a basis of mutual respect; (2) to develop an aggressive cooperative program for the churches in the interest of the Kingdom of God; (3) to encourage and assist in the formation and development of local councils" ("The Bylaws of the Michigan Council of Churches, 1928). Original members of the MCC represented exclusively Protestant communions and included Baptist, Congregational, Disciples, Methodist, Presbyterian, and Reformed in U.S.A. congregations. In addition to Executive and Finance Committees, the MCC's main units focused on evangelism, comity and interchurch cooperation, religious education, and public welfare.
On June 4, 1934, a 'Committee of Fourteen' comprised of seven appointees from both the MCC and the Michigan Council of Religious Education met to explore how the two organizations could work more efficiently in a broader range of fields. The meeting resulted in a recommendation that the two councils merge under the MCC banner, with tentative officers installed by January 1936 and the permanent organization established by January 1937 (a feat actually accomplished in October 1936).
As it matured, the MCC's overall purpose became "to exert spiritual and Christian leadership and to bring churches into living contact with one another for fellowship, study and cooperative action." Over time, this open-ended statement of purpose enabled the MCC to serve as a clearinghouse for ecumenical action on social reform. Issues such as church location, world hunger, Christian education, protest against the Vietnam War, Indian and migrant missions, criminal justice, pastoral education, and race relations found their way onto the MCC agenda from 1957 through 1986. In theory, the organizational structure of the MCC provided a framework within which social reform and ecumenical concerns could be addressed. This structure established a neat hierarchy of an annual General Assembly overseeing a board of directors and executive committee, which, in turn, presided over the various departments and divisions.
In practice, this hierarchical structure did not conform to the reality of changing social concerns. For example, the Council's opposition to the war in Vietnam saw a surge of activism that did not fit existing categories. When faced with such situations, the MCC modified its constitution and altered its organizational structure, usually at the division level, to accommodate the new reform impulse. Between 1957 and 1986 there were four such restructurings, a clear indication of the flexibility and changing sense of mission of the MCC. The 1957 constitution called for four divisions: Education, Life and Work, Missions, and Strategy and Church Planning. The 1964 version replaced the Life and Work Division with Church in Society, and it added the Christian Unity Division. The MCC devoted efforts to Christian education, missions, and development of churches, but it soon became apparent that two Church in Society subcommittees: Citizens Concerned About Vietnam and the Peace Education Program, commanded much of the MCC's attention and resources. This reality led to a twenty-eight month experiment, "MCC-28" during which a Program Development Table identified issues of concern and allocated resources to task forces formed to deal with specific problems. In this way the MCC was able to bring constitutionally-defined structures more in line with its actual activities. The flexible response allowed the Program Development Table to treat anti-Vietnam protest as program units of the MCC. The 1977 constitution reflected a similar issue-oriented organization functioning via task forces.
Throughout the 1970s, MCC task forces dealt with an increasingly broad array of issues that included criminal justice, living and working conditions of migrant farm workers, world hunger, welfare reform, and peace. Faced with limited funds during Michigan's lean years in the early 1980s, the MCC realized that it could not be all things to all people. Mindful of a need to adapt in light of changes to itself and society, the MCC initiated a discussion of its future as early as 1978. By 1980, the organization realized that its vision for Christian unity needed an ecumenical vehicle more far-reaching and inclusive and so it opted to focus its efforts on developing a more extensive ecumenical presence in Michigan and at the same time downplay the role of its task forces. The result was an extensive Consultation on the Future of Ecumenism that stretched from 1980 to 1985 and was guided by a steering committee of MCC officials and denominational heads.
The first phase of this Consultation (1980-1982) sought to articulate the changing ecumenical landscape in Michigan and how the MCC could respond while the second (1982-1984) developed plans to implement this vision. The final phase (1985) garnered support for a new ecumenical organization through the adoption of basic principles and Articles of Agreement by interested congregations and communions. 1985 and 1986 saw further work by the transition committee as well as three State Ecumenical Forums that paved the way for the commemoration of MCC's 'death'on October 23, 1986 and its rebirth as the Michigan Ecumenical Forum (MEF) on the following day.
The MEF was officially constituted on January 1, 1987 and, as an inclusive interfaith group, welcomed Roman Catholic and Orthodox denominations. The organization preserved the MCC's tradition of holding General Assemblies; these State Ecumenical Forums provided delegates the opportunity to vote on programs and projects as well as members of the State Ecumenical Coordinating Committee (SECC, the successor to the MCC Board of Directors). Between General Assemblies, the SECC was the main decision-making body of the MEF; it was comprised of up to 39 individuals from a diversity of participating denominations and was headed by the MEF Chair. The MEF Executive Director also held a non-voting seat on the SECC and was the head of the Executive Committee, a body that provided general organizational oversight and was empowered to make decisions when the SECC was unable to meet.
Although it represented a new start for the ecumenical movement in Michigan, the MEF carried on important objectives of its predecessor, including continued support for the development of Regional Ecumenical Forums. At the same time, the MEF consolidated its committees to address issues related to personnel, budget and finance, ecumenical mission, assembly planning, and Coordinating Committee nominations. The revised constitution also permitted the creation of ad hoc action committees and task teams to address specific issues or areas of concern as they emerged.
The MEF last filed an annual report in 2001; after Executive Director Candyce Williams' untimely death on April 26, 2002, the organization appears to have fallen rapidly into decline. According to the Michigan Department of Energy, Labor, and Economic Growth, the MEF was slated for automatic dissolution on October 1, 2004.
The records of the Michigan Ecumenical Forum (MEF) reflect the large-scale cooperation between various Christian denominations as well as ecumenical activities in relation to evangelical missions, Christian education, and pressing social issues. Administrative records and correspondence of governing bodies and committees document the regular operation of the MCC and MEF and materials related to activities such as Vietnam War protests, peace education, and ministry for migrant workers reveal the organization to be intimately involved in its community and a strong proponent for social justice. This collection will be of value to those interested in the history of Christian education and interfaith cooperation in Michigan as well as the role played by the church in the social activism of the 1960s and beyond. Upon their initial accession to the Bentley Historical Library, record series were constructed according to constitutional revisions; the present arrangement seeks a more organic coherence by uniting materials based upon function and the office of the creator. The Michigan Ecumenical Forum records are divided into three series: Administration, Organizational Activities and Units, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Anti-racism--Michigan.; Christian education--Michigan--History.; Ecumenical movement--Michigan.; Interdenominational cooperation--Michigan.; Michigan Council of Churches.; Missions--Michigan.; Michigan--Church history.; Migrant workers--Missions--Michigan.; Native Americans--Missions--Michigan.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Michigan.; Michigan Ecumenical Forum.; Peace education--Michigan.; Rural missions--Michigan.
Contributors:
Michigan Council of Churches.; Michigan Sunday School Association.; Michigan Council of Religious Education.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administration
  The Administration series contains the planning materials and records of general assemblies; early records and content related to predecessor organizations; and the records of governing bodies and committees (including the Constitution and Bylaw, Finance and Budget, and Strategic Planning committees among others). The series documents various reorganizations (including the Consultations on the Future of Ecumenism in Michigan that resulted in the MCC's rebirth as the MEF) as well as the evolution of the MCC/MEF's constitution, governance (Board of Directors, Program Development Table, and State Ecumenical Coordinating Committee), and goals. Also present are personnel files of executive directors and other officers as well as printed materials that include news clippings and MCC/MEF newsletters.
  - Assemblies and State Ecumenical Forums
    - Annual reports and agendas 1940-1976, 21 folders (Box 1)
      (missing 1942, 1946, 1956, 1958-1959)
    - Correspondence 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Planning materials, agendas and correspondence
      - 1985-1986, 5 folders; includes 7 audio cassette recordings of the April 1986 State Ecumenical Forum in Grand Rapids (Box 1)
      - 1987-1994, 26 folders (Box 2)
      - 1994-2001, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - Guidelines 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Committees
    - Budget and Finance
      (includes related financial materials)
      - Financial records, budgets, and correspondence 1955-1983, 17 folders (Box 3)
        (missing material from 1978-1979)
      - Financial records, budgets, and correspondence 1984-2002 (incomplete materials) (Box 4)
      - Real property 1956-1957, 1984-1986, 6 folders (Box 4)
        (includes photographs)
      - MEF Endowment Fund 1988-1995, 2001, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Constitution and Bylaws
      - Document revisions and official versions
        - 1945-1957 (Box 4)
        - 1964-1995 (Box 4)
      - Meeting materials, correspondence, and reports
        - 1962-1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - 1971 (Box 4)
        - 1991 (Box 4)
    - Membership and Relationships: clippings, correspondence, directories, etc. 1962-2001, 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Nominating: meeting minutes, correspondence, and slates 1987-1996, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Personnel: meeting minutes, correspondence, and job descriptions 1965-1996, 11 folders (Box 5)
    - Strategic Planning
      (includes planning materials from other committees)
      - Correspondence 1964-1969 (Box 5)
      - Meeting minutes, memoranda, and related materials: 1958-1968, 8 folders (Box 5)
      - Position statements 1970-1981 (Box 5)
      - Program Committee materials 1977-1980, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
      - Projects
        - Northport Report 1965 (Box 5)
        - Co-op Ministries 1966-1967 (Box 5)
        - Vacationland Workshop 1967 (Box 5)
        - Consultation on Church Location 1968 (Box 5)
      - Resolutions 1964-1969 (Box 5)
      - Working papers, reports, and proposals 1956-1998, 7 folders (Box 6)
        (includes the MCC-28 planning document)
    - Other
      - Assemblies 1993-1994 (Box 6)
      - Courtesy 1965-1970 (Box 6)
      - Ecumenical Mission 1997-1998 (Box 6)
      - Friends of MEF 1983-1993 (Box 6)
      - Interchurch Office Center 1963-1964 (Box 6)
      - Justice and Service 1992-1993 (Box 6)
      - Property 1988 (Box 6)
      - Taxation and the Church 1975-1979 (Box 6)
  - Early Records and Predecessor Organizations
    - Michigan Sunday School Association
      (also known as the Michigan Sunday School Council of Religious Education and the Michigan Council of Religious Education)
      - Articles of Association (and amendment) 1916, 1926 (Box 6)
      - Certificate of Dissolution 1936 (Box 6)
      - One hundredth anniversary research materials 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Records held by the Michigan Historical Commission Archive Dept. 1961 (Box 6)
      (item list of records from 1886-1960)
  - Governance
    - "Blue Books": yearly authorized records of action of the MCC containing the minutes of the general assembly, Board of Directors, and the Executive Committee
      - Description of the Contents of Blue Record Books 1968 (Box 6)
        (covers 1964-1968)
      - 1928-1936 (Box 7)
      - 1964-1968, 4 volumes (Box 7)
      - 1969-1972, 4 volumes (Box 8)
      - 1973-1975, 3 volumes (Box 9)
      - 1976-1977, 2 volumes (Box 10)
      - 1978-1981, 4 volumes (Box 11)
    - Administrative staff meeting minutes and memoranda 1965-1967 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence
      - 1967-1971, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - 1980-2002, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Board of Directors: minutes, correspondence, and related materials
      (additional materials for 1964-1981 located in the "Blue Books")
      - 1953-1963, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - 1982-1986, 4 folders (Box 12)
    - Executive Committee: minutes, correspondence, and related materials
      - 1962-1964 (Box 12)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 12)
      - 1981-1986, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - 1990-1999 (Box 13)
    - Officers
      - General lists 1947-1965 (Box 13)
      - Installation of Directors 1960s-1980s (Box 13)
      - Reports of the Executive Director
        - 1965-1968 (Box 13)
        - 1981-1988, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Program Development Table 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - State Ecumenical Coordinating Committee (SECC)
      (succeeded the Board of Directors after the MCC became the MEF)
      - Board directories and curricula vitae 1986-2001 (Box 13)
      - Meeting minutes, correspondence, and related materials
        - 1986-1995, 50 folders (Box 13)
        - 1995-2002, 29 folders (Box 14)
      - Yearly collections of SECC activities, memoranda, and reports
        - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 14)
          (unarranged)
        - 1987-1998, 10 folders (Box 15)
          (unarranged; missing 1995 and 1997)
  - Personnel Files
    - Bassett, Wendell (Executive Director) 1965-1968 (Box 15)
    - Benallack, William (Associate Director, Division of Christian Mission) 1964 (Box 15)
      (includes photograph)
    - Brown, Nelson (Director of Peace Education) 1973-1976 (Box 15)
    - Bruun, Arril "Archie" (Director, Michigan Farm Worker Ministry) 1971-1974 (Box 15)
    - Crouch, Arthur E. "Ted" (Associate Executive Director) 1972-1974 (Box 15)
    - Fisher, Robert (Treasurer) undated (Box 15)
    - Frears, Robert (Associate Director, Division of Christian Education) 1966-1967 (Box 15)
    - Kearns, Jr., Raymond V. (Executive Director) 1974-1976 (Box 15)
    - Kidd, Samuel E. (Executive Director) 1969-1973 (Box 15)
    - Lord, Harry J. (Director) 1961 (Box 15)
    - McKinney, Harold C. (Associate Director, Division of Church in Society) 1963-1964 (Box 15)
    - Mielke, William C. (Director of Continuing Education) 1972-1973 (Box 15)
    - Mondol, Harold (Associate Director, Division of Church in Society) 1965-1967 (Box 15)
    - Rozendaal, John (Program Director, Michigan Migrant Ministry) 1969-1976 (Box 15)
    - Vore, Duane N. (Executive Director) 1975-1978 (Box 15)
  - Printed Materials
    - Clippings and articles 1960-1988 (Box 16)
    - MEF media packet 1986 (Box 16)
    - "Milestones in MEF History" 2002 (Box 16)
    - Newsletters
      - "The Collaborator" 1943-1947 (Box 16)
      - "News Nuggets" 1955 (Box 16)
      - "Spot News" 1966-1968 (Box 16)
      - "Action" 1971 (Box 16)
      - "Council News" 1973-1978, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - "The Time Has Come" 1982-1986 (Box 16)
      - "Michigan Ecumenical Forum Newsletter" 1987-1993, 1998, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Press releases 1974-1996 (Box 16)
    - Publications: pamphlets, brochures, and reports 1962-1982 (Box 16)
  - Reorganization: Consultations on the Future of Ecumenism in Michigan
    - Reports on ecumenism 1982-1985 (Box 16)
    - Steering Committee
      - Brown (Patricia): personal notes and correspondence 1980-1985 (Box 16)
      - Meeting materials, correspondence, and related materials 1979-1985, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Transition Committee (MCC, MEF, and School for Ministry) 1984-1985 (Box 16)
    - Other
      - Address system and mailing protocols 1980s (Box 16)
      - File cabinet manifests 1985-1987 (Box 16)
      - Subscriptions and memberships 1982 (Box 16)
- Organizational Activities and Units
  The Organizational Activities and Units series consists of planning materials, meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence related to the MCC/MEF's operations. The series is divided into five subseries based upon longstanding (albeit frequently renamed) official divisions in the original MCC's activities (Church in Society, Education, Interchurch Unity and Cooperation, and Missions and Outreach) as well as General Issues, Initiatives, and Partnerships unassociated with specific initiatives.
  - Church in Society
    The Church in Society subseries reflects the activities of the Division of Church in Society, Division of Christian Life and Work, the Program Development table. It highlights the role of the MCC/MEF in social issues such as civil rights and race relations, activism against the Vietnam War (especially CALCAV, Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam), and planning materials and correspondence related to the Peace Education Program. The subseries also contains information related to legislative issues as well as the MCC publications Lansing Legislative Memo (a newsletter on political events at the state capital) and Legislative Principles (an annual pamphlet that detailed MCC's priorities in local and state politics).
    - General: meeting minutes and related correspondence
      (includes material from the Division of Christian Life and Work and Division of Church in Society)
      - 1954-1965, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - 1983 (Box 17)
    - Aging
      - Agreement between the Michigan Office of Services to the Aging and the Michigan Ecumenical Forum 1997 (Box 17)
      - Seminars 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Chavez Avenue (in Lansing) Name Controversy 1995 (Box 17)
    - Children's issues
      - General 1981 (Box 17)
      - "Covering Michigan's Kids and Families Proposal" 2001 (Box 17)
    - Civil rights and race relations
      - 1947 (Box 17)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 17)
    - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam (CALCAV)
      (originally Clergy Concerned about Vietnam (CCVN))
      - General: meeting minutes, reports, and related materials 1967-1972, 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Branches and regional activity
        - Detroit 1968-1970 (Box 17)
        - Flint 1969-1970 (Box 17)
        - Saginaw 1970-1971 (Box 17)
      - Congressional candidates' reactions 1968 (Box 17)
      - Correspondence in 1967-1972, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - Correspondence out 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 17)
      - Correspondence out 1970-1971 (Box 18)
      - Demonstrations and other activities
        - Anti-ABM March and Conference 1969 (Box 18)
        - Daily Death Toll Project 1971 (Box 18)
        - Dinners
          - Chomsky, Noam 1972 (Box 18)
          - Spock, Dr. Benjamin 1969 (Box 18)
          - Wald, George 1970 (Box 18)
          - Young, Andrew 1969 (Box 18)
        - Dow Chemical Corporation demonstrations 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Draft counseling workshops 1967-1968 (Box 18)
        - Letherer (Father Kenneth) organizing activities 1968-1971, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Paris trip (March 1971) 1970-1971 (Box 18)
        - Selfridge Airforce Base demonstration January-February, 1971 (Box 18)
        - Spring Campaign 1972 (Box 18)
        - Washington Mobilization 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Death Penalty 1974-1976, 1985 (Box 18)
    - Economic crisis in Michigan 1983 (Box 18)
    - Educational Exchange Program Agreement 1952 (Box 18)
      (contract with the United States Government regarding German exchange students)
    - International relations 1967-1968 (Box 18)
    - Legislative activities
      - Lansing Legislative Memo (newsletter), 1965-1968 (Box 18)
      - Legislative Information Committee 1963-1964 (Box 18)
      - Legislative issues
        - Council Against Parochaid and Citizens to Advance Public Education 1968-1973, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Committee on State Aid to Non-Public Schools 1968-1969 (Box 18)
        - Governor's Commission on Educational Reform 1969 (Box 18)
        - Proposed religious practitioner legislation 1991 (Box 18)
        - Sex education 1969 (Box 18)
        - State School Board Mission Statement 1997 (Box 18)
      - Legislative Principles (MCC publication) and related correspondence and reports, 1963-1970, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Seminars 1965-1971, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Peace Education Program (PEP)
      - General: meeting minutes, memoranda, and reports 1967-1971, 1974, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Correspondence in 1968-1971, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Correspondence out 1968-1971, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Draft counseling and conscientious objector training 1970-1971 (Box 19)
      - Films: promotional materials, study guides, and related materials 1969-1971 (Box 19)
      - Michigan military contractors 1969-1971 (Box 19)
      - National and local priorities in spending